Welcome to the Plutus Pioneer Program.
We are very excited to have you all here.
So, let me first talk about the schedule.
So the idea is that there will
be lectures on every Thursday and
Q & A sessions on every Tuesday.
And in some weeks we might have
additional lectures, for example, guest
lectures or some topics that are not
so relevant for the main curriculum.
And because there are so many of you,
it's unfortunately not possible to
be as interactive as I like it to be.
So it would be great if all of you could
use the discord server to help each other,
answer questions and solve problems.
I mean, we will do what we can, my colleagues
and myself to answer questions and help.
But with the sheer number of participants,
it's just not possible to pay as much
attention to every individual as we would like.
So thank you for helping out.
As for the content, so the idea is to
really give a thorough introduction to
Plutus, explain the underlying concepts,
look at various types of contracts.
Look at how we can test contracts in
the playground or also offline, locally.
Talk about native tokens, how to control
minting and burning of naked tokens in Plutus.
And we also look at how to deploy a Plutus
contract and write a back-end for Plutus contract.
Plutus learning is not easy unfortunately.
So, you have to be aware that the
cost probably won't be easy and there
are a variety of reasons for that.
So one is that Plutus uses
the so-called UTxO model.
I'll explain in much more detail what
that means later in this lecture, and that
is different and less intuitive than the
Ethereum method for doing smart contracts.
It has a lot of advantages the UTxO
model, but it also requires a new way
of thinking about smart contracts.
So that's one thing, and that's before
we even start with the language itself.
Then of course Plutus has brand new
and still under rapid development.
So probably during the time of the
course there will be significant changes.
So we often have to update the
dependencies on the main Plutus repository.
And it might be that contracts that compile at the
beginning of the course won't compile any longer
at the end of towards the end of the course,
because there have been some syntax changes.
In addition to that tooling is not ideal yet.
So those of you who have experienced with
Haskell and know about the Haskell tooling,
we noticed that in the presence of Plutus,
some of the tooling is not as pleasant as
you maybe use to being from doing Haskell.
So, sometimes it's a bit painful, so it's not
as easy to get access to a syntax of functions
or to documentation from the repl, for example.
And it's not even very easy to
build Plutus in the first place.
So your best bet is probably using nix.
You can also try cabal and Stack or
Docker, actually the Plutus team will
provide a nice Docker image at some point.
So maybe that will then be the easiest
option, but yeah, it's not totally trivial
to get Plutus to compile in the first place.
Then, of course, Plutus is Haskell more or less.
So on top of the other problems, you first
have to have a firm grip on a Haskell in
order to do Plutus and obviously in the eight
weeks, of course time, I won't have time to
first do a proper thorough Haskell course.
The Haskell course that I did in
Greece on Barbados in Ethiopia.
And then last year, virtually in
Mongolia were full-time courses, 10
week full-time courses, 40 hours a week.
And even in those courses, we didn't cover
everything that you will need to fully
understand Plutus, of course we also covered
things that are irrelevant for Plutus.
So it's not as bad as it sounds, but nevertheless,
there is a quite some Haskell that you need.
And I won't have time to
thoroughly explain everything.
I'll try to explain the special concepts
that you need for Plutus obviously, and
whenever there is a especially need, when
I see that a lot of you are struggling with
something, then obviously I'll take the
time to explain that topic in more detail.
So, unfortunately I won't be able to spend
as much time teaching Haskell as I'd like to,
because obviously I mostly want to do Plutus,
but we did recoat our Mongolia Haskell course.
And we have started editing the videos
and making them nicer and more concise.
And what we have, we'll publish here for you on
the discord server, so that, if you are struggling
with Haskell and would like an introduction,
that's much slower, much slower pace, then you
can give those videos a try, and maybe they
help with the Haskell problems you might have.
Another problem is that Plutus is brand
new, which of course is also very exciting,
but it also means that you and I and the
Plutus team are the first people ever in the
history of humanity that write Plutus code.
So if you learn another programming language and
you get stuck or have a problem, then normally
you can just go to stack overflow or Google,
and often you will be lucky and find an answer.
So, because we are the first
you won't have that option.
So we have to figure it out while we go along.
One of the most important things you need
to understand in order to write Plutus smart
contracts is the counting model that Cardano uses.
And that is the so-called (E)UTxO model,
which is an abbreviation for extended
unspent transaction output model.
The UTxO model without being extended is
the one that has been introduced by Bitcoin.
But there are other models.
Ethereum, for example, uses a so-called
account-based model, which is what you're used
do from a normal bank, where everybody has
an account and each account has a balance.
And if you transfer money from one
account to another, then the balances
get updated accordingly, but that
does not how the UTxO model works.
Unspent transaction outputs
are exactly what the name says.
They are transaction outputs that is outputs
from previous transactions that happened on
the blockchain that have not yet been spent.
So let's look at an example where we have
two such UTxOs, one belonging to Alice, 100
ADA and another one belonging to Bob, 50 ADA.
And as an example, let's assume that
Alice wants to send 10 ADA to Bob.
So she creates a transaction and the
transaction is something that has inputs
and outputs, can be an arbitrary number of
inputs and an arbitrary number of outputs.
And an important thing is that you can
always only use complete UTxOs as input.
So, if she wants to send 10 ADA
to Bob, she can't simply split her
existing 100 ADA into a 90 to 10 piece.
She has to use the full 100 ADA as input.
So by using the UTxO 100 ADA
as input to a transaction.
Alice has no spent that UTxO,
so it's no longer an UTxO.
It's no longer unspent it's been spent.
And now she can create outputs for a transaction.
So she wants to pay 10 ADA to Bob.
So one output will be 10 ADA to Bob,
and then she wants her change back.
So she creates a second
output of 90 ADA to herself.
And so this is how, even though
you always have to consume complete
UTxOs, you can get your change back.
So you consume the complete UTxO, but then
you create an output for the change and note
that in a transaction, the sum of the input
values must equal the sum of the output values.
So in this case, 100 ADA go
in and 10 plus 90 ADA go out.
This is strictly speaking, not true.
There are two exceptions, the first
exception is transaction fees.
So in the real blockchain for each
transaction, you have to pay fees.
So that means that the, some of input values
have to, has to be slightly higher than the sum
of output values to accommodate for the fees.
And the second exception is the
native tokens that we have on Cardano.
So it's possible for transactions
to create new tokens.
In which case the outputs will be higher than
the inputs or to burn tokens, in which case
the inputs will be higher than the outputs.
But that is a somewhat advanced
topic, how to handle minting and
burning of native tokens in Plutus.
And we'll come back to that later in the course.
So for now we only look at transactions
where there's some of the input values
equals the sum of the output values.
So this is a first example of a simple
transaction, and we see that the effect
of a transaction is to consume and spend
transaction output and to produce new ones.
So in this example, one UTxO has been
consumed, Alice original 100 ADA UTxO,
and two new ones have been created.
One 90 ADA UTxO belong to Alice and
another 10 ADA UTxO belonging to Bob.
It's important to note that this is the only
thing that happens on an UTxO blockchain.
The only thing that happens when a new transaction
is added to the blockchain is that some
form a UTxOs becomes spent and UTxOs appear.
So in particular, nothing is ever changed,
no value or any other data associated with
the transaction output is ever changed.
The only thing that changes by a new transaction
is that some of the formerly unspent transaction
outputs disappear and others are created,
but the outputs themselves never change.
The only thing that changes is
whether they are unspent or not.
Let's do one other example, a slightly
more complicated one where Alice and Bob
together want to pay 55 ADA each to Charlie.
So they create a transaction together.
And as inputs, Alice has no choice, she
only has one UTxO, so she uses that one.
And Bob also doesn't have a choice
because neither of his two UTxOs
is a large enough to cover 55 ADA.
So Bob has to use both his UTxO as input.
This time we need three outputs, one the
55 plus 55 equals 110 ADA for Charlie,
and then two change outputs, one for
Alice's change and one for Bob's change.
So Alice paid 90, so she should
get 35 change and Bob paid 60.
So he should get five change.
One thing, I haven't yet explained is under which
conditions a transaction can spend a given UTxO.
Obviously it wouldn't be a good idea if
any transaction could spend arbitrary
UTxOs, if that was the case, then Bob could
spend Alice's money without her consent.
So the way it works is by adding signatures
to transactions, so for our first example,
our transaction one, because that consumes
an UTxO belong to Allice as input.
Alice's signature has to be
added to the transaction.
And in the second example, because there
are inputs belonging to both Alice and
Bob, both Alice and Bob have to sign
that transaction, which incidentally
is something you can't do in Daedalus.
So you would have to use the Cardano
CLI for complex transactions like that.
Everything I've explained so far is just about
the UTxO model, not the extended UTxO model.
So this is all just a simple UTxO model.
And the extended part comes in
when we talk about smart contracts.
So in order to understand that,
let's just concentrate on one
consumption offer a UTxO buy an input.
And as I just explained, the validation
that decides whether the transaction.
This input belongs to is allowed to
consume that you take so in the simple
UTxO model relies on digital signatures.
So in this case, Alice has to sign the transaction
for this consumption of the UTxO to be valid.
And now the idea of the extended UTxO
model is to make this more general.
So instead of just having one condition,
namely that the appropriate signatures
is present in the transaction.
We replace this by arbitrary logic,
and this is where Plutus comes in.
So instead of just having an address that
corresponds to a public key, and that can
be verified by a signature that is added
to the transaction, instead we have more
general addresses that are not based on
public keys or the hashes of public keys,
but instead contain arbitrary logic that
can decide under which condition this
specific UTxO can be spent by a transaction.
So instead of an address going to a
public key, like Alice's public key in
this example, there will be an arbitrary
script, a script containing arbitrary logic.
And instead of the signature in the transaction,
the input will justify that it is allowed
to consume this output with some arbitrary
piece of data that we call the redeemer.
So we replace the public key address,
Alice in our example by a script, and we
replace a digital signature by a redeemer
which is an arbitrary piece of data.
Now, the next question is,
what exactly does that mean?
What do we mean by arbitrary logic?
And in particular it's important
to consider what information?
What context this script has?
So there are several options.
And the one indicated in this diagram is
that all the script sees is the redeemer.
So all the information the script has
in order to decide whether it's okay
for the transaction to consume this
UTxO or not is looking at the redeemer.
And that is the thing that
Bitcoin incidentally does.
So, in Bitcoin, there are smart
contracts, they are just not very smart.
They are called Bitcoin script and
Bitcoin script works exactly like this.
So there's a script on the UTxO site and to
redeemer on the input side and the script gets
the redeemer and can use the redeemer to decide
whether it's okay to consume the UTxO or not.
But that's not the only option, we can decide
to give more information to the script.
So, Ethereum uses a different concept.
In Ethereum the script basically can
see everything, the whole blockchain,
the whole state of the blockchain.
So that's like the opposite extreme of Bitcoin.
Bitcoin the script has very little context,
all it can see is the redeemer in Ethereum
the script, the solidity scripts in Ethereum
can see the complete state of the blockchain.
So that enables Ethereum's scripts to be
much more powerful so they can do basically
everything, but it also comes with problems
because the scripts are so powerful, it's also
very difficult to predict what a given script
will do and that opens the door to all sorts
of security issues and dangerous, because it's
very hard to predict for the developers of
an Ethereum smart contract what can possibly
happen because there are so many possibilities.
So what Cardano does is something in
the middle, so it doesn't offer such
a restricted view as Bitcoin, but also
not such a, not such a global view as
Etherebut, but instead chooses a middle way.
So the script can see the whole blockchain, can
see the state of the word blockchain, but it can't
see the whole transaction that is being validated.
So, in contrast to Bitcoin it can just see
this one input, the redeem of this one input,
but it can see that and all the other inputs
of the transaction and also all the outputs of
the transaction and the transaction itself, and
the Plutus script can use that information to
decide whether it's okay to consume this output.
Now, in this example, there's only one input, but
if this transaction had more than one input, then
the script would be able to see those as well.
There's one last ingredient that Plutus
scripts need in order to be as powerful
as expressive as Ethereum scripts.
And that is a so-called datum which is
a piece of data that can be associated
with a UTxO an addition to the value.
So at a script address, like in this
example, in addition to this 100 ADA
value, that can be an arbitrary piece
of data attached, which we call datum.
And with this, we can actually mathematically
prove that Plutus is at least as powerful
as Ethereum, so everything, every logic
you can express in Ethereum you can also
express in this extended UTxO model that
Cardano uses, but it has a lot of important
advantages in comparison to the Ethereum model.
So for example, in Plutus, it is possible to
check whether a transaction will validate in
your wallet before you ever sent it to the chain.
So something can still go wrong, so for
example, your transaction can consume an
output and then when it gets to the chain,
somebody else has already consumed that output.
This output has already been
consumed by another transaction.
You can't prevent that, but in that
case, your transaction will simply fail
without you having to pay any fees.
But if all the inputs are still
there, that your transaction expects.
Then you can be sure that the transaction will
be validate and that it will have the effect that
you predicted when you ran it in your wallet.
And this is definitely not the case in Ethereum,
in Ethereum in the time between you constructing
the transaction and it being incorporated
into the blockchain, a lot of stuff can happen
concurrently and that's unpredictable, and that
can have unpredictable effects on what will
happen when your script eventually executes.
So that means in Ethereum it's always
possible that you have to pay guest fees
for a transaction, although the transaction
eventually fails with an error, and that
is guaranteed not to happen in Cardano.
In addition to that, it's also easier to
analyze a Plutus script and to check or
even proof that it is secure because you
don't have to consider the whole state
of the blockchain, which is unknowable.
You can concentrate on this context that
just consists of the spending transaction.
So you have a much more limited scope and
that makes it much easier to understand what a
script is actually doing and what can possibly
happen or what could possibly go wrong.
So this is it, that's the extended
UTxO model that Plutus uses.
So to recapitulate in extending the normal
UTxO model, we replace public key addresses
from the normal UTxO model with scripts,
Plutus scripts, and instead of legitimizing the
consumption of new UTxO by digital signatures,
as in the simple UTxO model, arbitrary data
it's called redeemer is used on the input side.
And we also add arbitrary
custom data on the output side.
And the script as context when it
runs, sees the spending transaction,
the transaction one, in this example.
So given the redeemer and the datum and
the transaction with its other inputs
and outputs, the script can run arbitrary
logic to decide whether it's okay for this
transaction to consume the output or not.
And that is how Plutus works.
One thing I haven't mentioned yet is who is
responsible for providing datum, redeemer
and the validator, the script that validates
whether a transaction can consume an input.
And the rule in Plutus is that the spending
transaction has to do that whereas the producing
transaction only has to provide hashes.
So that means if I produce an output that sits at
a script address, then this producing transaction
only has to include the hash of the script and
the hash of the datum that belongs to this output.
But optionally, it can include the datum and the
script as well, fully, but that's only optional.
And if a transaction wants to consume such
a script output, then that transaction,
the spending transaction has to include
the datum and the redeemer and the script.
So that's the rule, how it works in Plutus,
which of course means that in order to
be able to spend a given input, you need
to know the datum because only the hash
is publicly visible on the blockchain.
Which is sometimes a problem and not
what you want and that's where this
optional possibility comes into to also
include it in the producing transaction.
Otherwise only people that know the datum by
some other means not by looking at the blockchain
would be able to ever spend such an output.
So this is the UTxO model, the extended
unspent transaction output model.
And that is of course not tied to
a specific programming language.
I mean, what we have is Plutus, which is based
on Haskell, but in principle, you could use
the same concept, the same UTxO model with
a completely different programming language.
And we also plan to write compilers from other
programming languages to Plutus script which is
sort of the assembly language and aligned Plutus.
So there's an extended UTxO model is different
from the specific programming language we use.
In this course, we will use Plutus obviously,
but the understanding the UTxO model is
independently valid from understanding
Plutus or learning the Plutus, Plutus syntax.
And I planned this lecture and the course,
I first thought I, I should do it the
traditional way of starting very simple
and maybe give a crash introduction into a
Haskell, then do some simple Plutus contracts
and slowly add more complicated stuff.
But then I decided it would be more
interesting, especially for the first lecture
to showcase a more interesting contract
and just demonstrate what Plutus can do.
And then use that to look at certain concepts
in more detail and explain them in more detail.
So the code for this course we'll be in this
GitHub repository it's at input-outpu-hk,
and then plutus-pioneer-program.
So I have a local clone of this repository.
And the code for week one is in
the sub folder code slash week one.
And in order to build this, the
most reliable way is to use nix.
And for that, we need the right
dependency of the Plutus repository.
And that one is mentioned
in the cabal project file.
So we see here in this folder, there's this cabal
project file and if we look at that, then here,
this is the reference to the Plutus repository,
here you also can see the address on GitHub.
So it's input-output-hk/plutus.
And this is the tag we're
using for the code this week.
So this will change during the duration of the
course because Plutus is still under development.
So, stuffs has permanently changed and I'll try
to keep the lectures as up to date as possible.
So probably every week I
will change this dependency.
So once we have this, we can go to the
Plutus folder so I also have that locally,
clone of the Plutus repository and there we
must make sure that we have the right hash
so we can, for example, do a git log and
then this commit hash here must be the one
that's mentioned in the cabal project file.
If not, we have to use, git checkout with
that hash from the cabal project file.
And then we start the nix shell, I already
did this, so I won't execute this now.
So I'm already in a nix shell, but in this Plutus
repository folder we have to start a nix shell.
And when you do that for the first time,
it can take, take quite a while, and you
should also consult the readme of the Plutus
repository, how to configure nix, because you
have to use the appropriate caches so that you
don't have to build everything by yourself,
but can reuse the cache content then it's
much faster, otherwise it might take hours.
So once you have this nix shell, you
can then go back to the Plutus Pioneer
Program repo for the appropriate week,
and then build the code with cabal build.
And this will also take a while the first
time you do it, I did it before, so in
that case it's instantaneous, but the
first time will take quite some time.
So you need some patients, but that's the
most reliable way to do it and to build
the code that's accompanying this course.
As my introductory example, I
pick the example of an auction.
So the idea is somebody wants to
auction an NFT, a non fungible token.
That is a native token on Cardano that only exists
exactly once and NFT itself can represent some
digital art or maybe also some real world asset.
And the owner of the token
wants to auction it away.
And the idea is that this auction is
parameterized by the owner of the token
and the token itself, then a minimal bid.
So no bid below that minimum will
be accepted and the deadline.
So all the bids have to
arrive before the deadline.
So let's say that Alice has an
NFT and wants to auction it.
So she creates a UTxO at the script output
where the script is the auction script.
We will look at the code later, but first I
just want to explain the idea in the UTxO model.
And the value of that UTxO is just the NFT, and
the datum at the moment is nothing, later it
will be the highest bidder and the highest bid.
But right now there hasn't
been a bid, so it's nothing.
In the real blockchain you can't have a
UTxO that just contains native tokens.
They always have to be accompanied by some
ADA, but I'm ignoring this for simplicity here.
Now let's say that Bob wants to bid
100 ADA, maybe that's the minimal bit.
So in order to do this, Bob creates a
transaction with two inputs and one output.
And the first input is the auction UTxO.
The second input is Bob's bid, 100 ADA, and
the output is again at the auction script,
but now the value and the datum has changed.
So before the datum was just nothing,
because there hadn't been a bid yet.
Now it's just Bob and a hundred.
So it requires the highest bidder,
Bob and how high the bid was, 100.
The value has changed because now
there's not only the NFT contained in
this UTxO, but also the 100 ADA bid.
And as a redeemer in order to unlock the original
auction UTxO, we use something called bid.
So that's just an algebraic data type, there
would be other values as well but one of those
is bid and the script, the auction script will
check that all the conditions are satisfied.
So in this case, the script has to check that
the bid happens before the deadline, that the bid
is high enough higher than the minimal bid and
that the correct inputs and outputs are there.
So the auction is an input and also an output
that again contains the NFT and contains
the correct highest bid in addition to that,
and that the datum is updated correctly.
Next let's assume that Charlie
wants to outbid Bob and bid 200 ADA.
So Charlie will create another transaction.
This time one with two inputs and two outputs.
So, as in the first case, the two
inputs are Charlie's bid, the 200 ADA
and the auction UTxO and one of the
outputs is the updated auction UTxO.
So when I say updated, recall that
I earlier said nothing ever changes.
So the old auction UTxO is consumed is spent
and the new one is created, but it has this
feel of updating the state of the auction UTxO.
Anyway, so that gets updated.
So instead of NFT and 100 ADA will now contain
NFT and 200 ADA, then use higgest bid and also
the datum will reflect that now the highest
bidder is Charlie and the highest bid is 200.
And that will be an additional output
namely Bob will get his bid back.
And that's also the reason, one of the
reasons we have to recall the highest
bidder and the highest bid so that we know
who will get the old highest bid back.
And in this case we again use the bid
redeemer, but now the script has to check as
before that the deadline has not been reached
test to check that the new highest bid is
actually higher than the old highest bid.
It has to check that the new
auction UTxO is correctly updated.
And it also has to make sure that
the original highest bidder, Bob
in this case gets his bid back.
Finally, let's assume that there won't
be another bid, so once the deadline has
been reached, the auction can be closed.
In order to do that, somebody has to create
yet another transaction, that could be Alice
who wants her bid or it could also be Charlie
who wants the NFT, it doesn't matter, it
can be anybody, but those two actually have
an incentive to create this transaction.
So this transaction will have one input,
just the auction UTxO with redeemer close,
not bid in this case and two outputs.
And one of the outputs is the highest bidder,
Charlie, and he gets the NFT, he won the auction.
So he gets what was auctioned away
and Alice, the owner of the auction,
the original owner of the NFT.
She gets the highest bid and that closes
the auction and finished this scenario.
And the script in the close case has to
check that the deadline has been reached
and that the highest bidder gets the NFT and
that the auction owner gets the highest bid.
There's one more scenario for us to
consider namely that nobody made any bid.
So, Alice starts the auction,
but then nobody creates a bid.
And in this case, there must be a
mechanism for Alice to retrieve her NFT.
So for that, she creates a transaction
again with the close redeemer.
But now, because there is no bidder,
the NFT doesn't go to the highest
bidder because there is no highest
bidder, but simply goes back to herself.
So the logic in this case, if there's no highest
bidder is likely different for the close redeemer,
it must check that the NFT goes back to Alice.
Actually, it doesn't have to check anything
because I mean, this will be triggered by Alice.
Alice will create this transaction.
And of course she could send
the NFT wherever she wants.
Let's have a brief look at the code,
but don't worry, I don't expect
you to understand it at this point.
It's an important thing to realize about Plutus
is that there's on-chain and off-chain code.
On-chain code is this script we were
discussing in the script from the UTxO model.
So in addition to public key addresses,
we have script addresses and outputs
can sit at such a script address.
And if a transaction tries to consume such
an output, the script is executed and only
if it succeeds, the transaction is valid.
So how it works is if a node receives a new
transaction, it validates it before accepting
it into its mempool and eventually into a block.
And for each input of the transaction, if
that input happens to be a script address, the
corresponding script is executed and must succeed.
And if it doesn't succeed, then
the transaction is invalid.
So that's the so-called on-chain aspect of
Plutus and the programming language this
script is expressed in as written in is
called Plutus core, but you never write plutus
core by hand, instead you write Haskell and
then that gets compiled down to Plutus core.
And eventually there may also very well be
other higher level programming languages,
like maybe solidity or C or Python that
can compile it down to Plutus core.
So that's the one thing that's the
script and the task of a script is to say
yes or no can this transaction consume
the output I'm locking, yes or no?
But in order to actually use such an output
that is locked at the script address.
So in order to create a transaction that will
unlock section output and use that input,
you of course must be able to construct a
transaction that will then pass validation.
And that is the responsibility
of the off-chain part of Plutus.
So there is a part that runs in the wallet,
not on the blockchain, and that will
construct suitable transactions that are
then able to unlock a given script output.
So that's like a dual role of on-chain and
off-chain, on chain checks and validates, it
doesn't do anything, it just says yes or no.
And the off-chain part constructs actively creates
a transaction that will then pass validation.
And the nice thing, or one of the nice things
about Plutus is that both the on-chain and
the off-chain parts are written in Haskell.
So one obvious advantage of that
is that you don't have to learn two
programming languages, just one Haskell.
And the other advantage is that you can share
code between on-chain and off-chain part.
Later in this course we will talk about state
machines, then this aspect is even more direct,
there you can really use the same, literally the
same code, both for checking and for construction.
But even if you don't use state machines there's
still a lot of possibility to share code.
So if we briefly look at the code, so
here, for example, it's just a Haskell
data type that defines an auction.
So it's the seller, the deadline, the minimal
bid and then the last two define the NFT
and various other data types .And here,
this is the heart of the on-chain code.
So this defines the script, the logic
of the script, that validates where the
transaction is allowed to spend a given
output sitting at this auction contract.
So there are various helper
functions here to do that.
And so this is that.
And then here, this is where
the compilation happens.
So the, this functionary address shorter it's just
Haskell, but then here you have something called
template Haskell to activate the GHC plug in that
then compiles, this Haskell code to Plutus core.
And here the off-chain part starts,
which defines various parameters for
endpoints that can be then invoked.
So we have three endpoints for this example,
start will be used by the seller to start
the auction, to log the NFT into the
auction contract and then bid and close.
So bid obviously will be used by bidders to
make a bid and close will be used either by
the winner of the auction or by the seller.
And so here, these operations are
defined, so this is the start logic.
Then we have the bid logic here.
Okay.
That's a bit further and then
finally here, the close logic.
And then some helper functions and this
just basically packages everything up.
It says, okay, we will have these
three endpoints start, bid and close.
And they are called start, bid and close.
And the last lines are just for demo purposes
or for trying it out in the playground to create
an sample NFT that we can use to auction away.
So that has nothing to do
with the actual contract.
And what I said about code reuse, for
example, if you look here at the bid off-chain
part that uses a function min bid here.
Basically determines giving on the current datum
on the state of the contract, whether there was
already a bid or not, determines the minimal bid.
And if we look for that, we
see that this is defined here.
And it's also used here we
are in the on-chain part.
So obviously this script must check if a
new bid comes in, whether it's high enough.
So it's useful to have function that
computes this minimal bid but also in the
off-chain part where I'm back to now, it's
also useful if the wallet before even bother
us constructing a transaction that makes a
bid, checks whether the bid is high enough.
That's not strictly speaking necessary, the
wallet could just construct the transaction
anyway, but then it would be doomed to fail.
So it would be stupid to actually
construct it in the first place.
That's why I have this check in here that
checks whether the bid is actually high enough.
But the point I want to make is that this
min bid helper function can be shared between
on-chain and off-chain code because it's
just a plane Haskell function and can be
used in both parts of the Plutus contract.
So that's a very nice aspect of Plutus that you
don't have code duplication between the on-chain
part that lives on the blockchain and this
responsible for validation and the off-chain
part that runs in the user's wallet on the user's
local machine, or later in the user's web browser.
And it's used to construct transactions
that will then pass a validation.
So it's important to keep these two uses
apart and then to realize what they are.
And sometimes it's confusing when
people talk about smart contracts
or contracts, what do they mean?
do they mean the script, the on-chain script?
Or do they mean the off-chain part that
lives in the wallet and run some wallet?
And it's even more confusing because
the Haskell data type used for the
off-chain part is also called contract.
So if you talk about contract, do you mean
this capital C contract, the off-chain contract
that's executed in, on the user's machine?
Or do we talk about something else?
So it's important to be precise about what
we actually mean when we discuss something.
Yes.
But just to summarize, so we have on-chain and
off-chain, on-chain gets compiled down to Plutus
core and is living on the blockchain and is
executed by nodes that validate transactions.
And if you have the off-chain code that lives
on the user's machine and is responsible
for constructing transactions and submitting
transactions, that will then unlog certain
script outputs and both are written in Haskell.
And that allows us to share code between
them, which avoids code duplication.
So we have a shorter code and basically
guaranteed that the parts fit together or these
it's easier to make the parts fit together.
Now, we want to try this in the
playground and we won't use the publicly
available playground because that's
outdated, that's from February I believe.
We want to use one that is in sync with the
version of Plutus we are using right now.
So we go back to the Plutus repository in a nix
shell to the sub folder plutus-playground-client.
And we start plutus-playground-server there.
Then we go to a different console, but the
same folder again in the nix shell and we
do npm start to start the playground client.
And then we can open this address in a
browser and find our playground there.
So first we would see the editor
window and we can just take the code
we just looked at and paste it in here.
And press compile to compile it and if all goes
well, that should compile without error message.
It does, now we can go to simulate and here we
have simulated wallets and can invoke endpoints.
So by default, there are only two wallets, but if
you want to replay the scenario I showed in the
UTxO diagram, you should create a third wallet.
And we see that by default, the opening
balances are just 10 lovelace and 10 of this
token, but I want this token to be an NFT.
So that doesn't make any sense anyway.
So let's say wallet one is Alice, wallet
two is Bob and wallet three is Charlie.
So Alice has the one T and that's the only
one we have, so for the other say zero and
10 lovelace, is of course, ridiculously low.
So make that, I don't know, a thousand
ADA, so one ADA is a million lovelace.
So 1, 2, 3, 1, 2, 3.
Let's give everybody the same.
Okay, so now we can invoke endpoints.
So Alice starts the auction.
We have to provide parameters,
the first one is the deadline.
Let's say the deadline is slot 10,
but time is measured in posix time.
So in seconds from 1st of January
1970 I believe, something like that.
So it's not so clear what value makes sense there.
Luckily in the plutus-ledger
package in module Ledger.TimeSlot.
There's a convenient function slot to posix time.
So if we import that in the repl.
Now we have this slot to posix time and if
we need to slot 10, you get this value here.
Probably I think the simulation always
start at the beginning of the Shelley era.
So probably if you convert it, it
will be sometime, some of 2020, but
in any case, we can use this value.
So let's use the value here.
Now the minimum bid, let's say 100 ADA, and now
we must specify the NFT that's being auctioned.
And because of how I set it
up, this is six, six and T.
So don't worry about the 66.
That's just how this T was defined.
Okay.
Now let's wait one block.
Now let's Bob make his bit.
So this is again, specify the NFT so it's 66 T.
Now the bid, 100 ADA, we wait for another block.
Now, Charlie outbids Bob, again the 66 and the T.
And now 200 ADA.
We wait until the deadline has been reached, let's
wait until just for good measure until slot 11.
I'm not sure whether 10 would suffice.
It depends how exactly before and
after the deadline is defined.
And then Alice or Bob or Charlie, anybody can
invoke close, but Bob has no reason to, so it
would be Alice or Charlie,  let's say Alice.
So she invokes the close endpoint, again 66 T and
let's wait for one more block and let's evaluate.
Okay, and now we see the
transactions that were simulated.
We see there were 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, which at first
glance is a bit weird because we only have start,
two bids and the close, so it should be four.
But the first one in slot zero is always there,
that's the so-called genesis transaction.
It's a transaction without input that
provides the initial funds to the wallets.
So we have these three outputs for our
three wallets and we get what we specified
so, Alice gets 1,000 ADA and the token
and two and three Bob and Charlie only
get 1,000 ADA but nothing of the token.
So this is the Genesis transaction
that always happens to kick things
off and provide initial funds.
So now in slot one, this should
be the start transaction.
So input we see is the only UTxO
that Alice owns the her 1,000 ADA.
And the, it contains 1,000 ADA and the NFT.
So this is the start transaction.
We see that fees are taken into account
here in the playground, but not properly.
I think there's always at the moment a flat
rate of 10 lovelace, which is not realistic.
So in, in the real blockchain, in the real system,
the fee will of course depend on the transaction,
how big it is and how long the scripts run,
how many resources they consume and so on.
But for now the fees always 10 lovelace.
Then the second output here is Alice's change.
So she gets her 1,000 ADA back
minus the 10 lovelace fee.
And the third output is the interesting
one that goes to the auction script.
So now the NFT is logged in the auction script.
So now if we go to the next
transaction, that should be Bob's bid.
So we have two inputs as in the
diagram we looked at earlier.
So one is the auction script with the
NFT and one is Bob's original UTxO.
And as outputs, so we're gonna have the fees
or which in this case are not just 10 lovelace.
So now we have like a higher fee.
So it seems that changed since
last time we looked at it.
So now it's not a flat rate of 10 lovelace
there is some more sophistication going on.
The second output is Bob's change.
So it's basically a 1,000 ADA minus the
130 bids, but then also minus the fee.
The third output is the updated script.
So the updated script now
contains the token and Bob's bid.
Now let's look at the next
transaction, the Charlie's bid.
So it's similar here on the input side.
So the script UTxO goes in, that at the
moment contains the NFT and Bob's bid.
Then Charlie's UTxO is the second input.
Now we have one output more
because Bob gets his bid back.
So we have the fees, we
have the change for Charlie.
So he gets roughly 800 ADA change
because he, his bid was 200.
Then we have the script output, so
the NFT is still there, but now there
are 200 ADA in it Charlie's bid.
And finally for wallet two for Bob, Bob
gets his 100 bid back and the last one
will be the close, invoked by Alice.
So input is just Alice's wallet, this is in order
to pay for the fees and then the script output.
And so we have the fees,
we have changed for Alice.
So it's virtually the same
that went in minus these fees.
Then Alice gets the highest bid
the 200 ADA and Bob gets the token.
So the auction has finished.
We could check what happens
if something goes wrong.
Or for example, if Charlie's bid is too
low, is not higher than, than Bob's bid.
So where is it?
That was here, the bid was 200, so
let's say Charlie makes a mistake and
only bids instead of 200, only 20 ADA.
So if we now evaluate.
Okay, then we see we have one transaction less.
So, this is still Bob's bid with the 100,
but now Charlie's transaction was invalid.
So that's rejected and the close now looks
different because now Bob is the highest bidder.
So Alice only gets 100 and Bob gets the NFT.
Finally, we can try what happens if there
is no valid bids So, for example, we
can just remove the bids all together,
let's remove Bob's bid and Charlie's bid.
And we must just wait until the deadline
has been reached, so wait until slots
11 let's say and see what happens now.
Okay.
So we have the genesis transaction and
the opening of the auction and no bids.
And now the closing of the auction will
just return the NFT here to Alice, so
in this case, there are two outputs to
Alice's address, but in any case, she
ends up with the NFT back in her hands.
So you can see that this is a relatively
complex contract and one that might actually
be useful in practice, and it seems to work
and we can play with it in the playground.
So I hope you enjoyed this walk
through through the auction contract.
And I excited to learn how to do things
like that, or even more interesting things
like that yourself during this course.
And that's the end of today's lecture.
So all that remains is homework.
So I've planned to give you a little bit of
homework every week so that you can practice
because in learning a programming language, it's
always very important that you try it yourself.
Because often, if you listen to a lecture,
even if you think you understand everything
then if you sit down and try it yourself, you
actually realize if there are certain things
you didn't really understand, as well as
you thought you did when you listened to it.
But of course we haven't
really learned anything yet.
So I can't ask you to write
a simple Plutus contract.
So for the first week, I would just
like to ask you to basically do
what I did in this walk through.
So clone the Plutus Pioneer Program repository,
get it to build with cabal build, clone the
Plutus repository, check out the right commit,
get the nix shell working, start the Plutus
playground server, start the Plutus playground
client, then copy paste the code from the
Plutus Pioneer Program repo into the playground.
And make it compile and then
simulate some auctions scenarios.
So it would be great if, if all of you could
manage to get that working, because then it means
that your environments are properly set up and
we're ready to take on more interesting things.
So that was it for the first week.
Thank you very much again, for attending
the course and talk to you next week.
Thank you.